Guide to the Memory Project Oral History collection, 2009-2016 | 民间记忆计划口述史 RL.10171
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Guangdong Province | 广东省, 2011-2013
  - Zhaixia Village | 河源市和平县彭寨镇寨下村, 2011-2012
    - Zeng Linjian | 曾林俭, 2011
      Zeng Linjian (b.1931) is a resident of Zhaixia Village, Pengzhai Town, Heping County, Heyuan City, Guangdong Province. As he recounts, after the communization, people ran out of food, and had to ate unpalatable leaves and had potato vines in place of tea. An old lady in the village carried a cage for chicken to steal wheats from the production team's fields; her aunt at home wanted to remarry someone for food. Zeng's father as well as her first and second husbands were all starved to death. In the family, she is the only senior alive now.
    - Chen Qianmei | 陈千妹, 2011
      Chen Qianmei (b. 1928) is a resident of Zhaixia Village, Pengzhai Town, Heping County, Heyuan City, Guangdong Province. According to Chen, after the communization, people did not have much food, but they still had to hand in their food to the commune. Adults could only eat dirty things and slices of sweet potatoes, so that their children could have some rice. Sometimes, Chen's husband shouldered limestones into towns to sell and bought some rice. He worked till late at night and came back home.
      陈千妹 (1928年生) 是广东省河源市和平县彭寨镇寨下村村民。陈老人回忆，公社化那几年人们没东西吃，还得交公粮，成年人为了省米粮给孩子们，只能吃脏东西和番薯片。曾经，老人的丈夫挑着石灰去城里卖，换米吃，工作到深夜才回来。
    - Luo Meiyu | 罗美玉, 2011
      Luo Meiyu (b. 1927) is a resident of Zhaixia Village, Pengzhai Town, Heping County, Heyuan City, Guangdong Province. Luo talked briefly about her life: She was born in Chaozhou, married three times, gave birth to 11 children, sold 3 sons because there were no enough food to feed them. She also talked about the hard labor in the field. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      罗美玉（1923年生）是广东省河源市和平县彭寨镇寨下村村民。罗老人大致讲了自己一生的经历：出生在潮州，嫁过三次，生了11个小孩，卖了3个儿子，因为粮食不够没法养。老人谈到在地里犁地耕地，非常辛苦。
    - Ye Shiying | 叶石英, 2011
      Ye Shiying (b.1938) is a resident of Zhaixia Village, Pengzhai Town, Heping County, Heyuan City, Guangdong Province. Ye recollects that, during the Great Famine, people could only get two tablespoons of porridge from the eating hall every day, and ate them with steamed sweet potato slices at home. She also ate many other kinds of famine food and she could hardly find potatoes in the mountains after working for a whole day. Many people starved to death after the communization, including people in the elderly homes and maternities. The production team sprinkled seeds instead of actually planting them; they had no harvest, but reported the opposite to the higher authorities.
      叶石英（1938年生）是广东省河源市和平县彭寨镇寨下村村民。叶老人叙述了饥荒期间，人们在食堂里每人只能领两小勺粥，回家蒸番薯片跟粥一起吃。她当时还吃吃糠饼、野菜、山将树叶等等，上山挖一天都挖不到一个薯粮。很多人在公社化期间被饿死，养老院和妇产院也断粮。生产队撒秧，而不插秧，没有收成，却对上级汇报滿产。
    - Ye Shengpeng | 叶升彭, 2012
      Ye Shengpeng (b.1942) is a resident of Zhaixia Village, Pengzhai Town, Heping County, Heyuan City, Guangdong Province. He recollects many people's dates of death. Not that many people in the village died, because they hid food at home. Their food was never found, so they did not suffer that much hunger as other places.
      叶升彭 （1942年生）围背村没饿死几个人，因为当时很多人偷偷留了粮食，没被搜出来，所以饥饿那几年饿得没其他地方厉害。
    - Ye Shiyang | 叶石扬, 2012
    - Ye Xinji | 叶新基, 2011
      Ye Xinji (b. 1927) is a resident of Zhaixia Village, Pengzhai Town, Heping County, Heyuan City, Guangdong Province. Ye recollects that during the collectivization, people farmed together and many just pretended to work, so they ran out of food. Ye and the interviewer Ye Zuyi's father often went fishing at night. He also went to Qingzhou with some other people to sell vats in return for sweet potatoes.
      叶新基（1927年生）是广东省河源市和平县彭寨镇寨下村村民。叶老人回忆了公社化的时候，大家一起种田，很多人偷懒，于是没有食物吃。叶老人和采访人叶祖艺的父亲晚上去河里抓鱼吃。他当时和其它几个人去青州卖缸，换番薯片吃。
    - Ye Xuanhua | 叶宣华, 2011
  - Guanchong Village | 茂名市高州市宝光街道办荷木坡管理区关冲村, 2013
    Guanchong Village is located in Gaozhou County, Maoming City, Guangdong Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Wu Haizhu.
    - Li Qunying | 李群英, 2013
      Li Qunying (b. 1939) is a resident of Guanchong Village, Guangdong Province. In this interview, Li talks about her lifelong hardship. Li's mother left home when she was 5, so she was raised by her father. After the Liberation, Li was sold to a family as their daughter. However, after frequently being beaten up, Li escaped several times and eventually went home with her father. She stayed at home until she got married in 1961. Due to the shortage of all kinds of materials, Li waited in line for a long time in order to get herself a pair of new shoes for the wedding. Later when she was working at the production team, in addition to the heavy workload, she had to get up before dawn to chop firewood. If she were late for work, her work points would be deducted. When the One-Child Policy was carried out, if someone did not have the vasectomy as required, his work points would be removed. In this interview, Li also sang many old songs.
      李群英1939年出生，是广东省高州市宝光街道办荷木坡管理区关冲村村民。在这段口述中，李老人回忆了自己艰苦的一生。李老人五岁时妈妈离家出走，由爸爸独自带大。解放后，十多岁的李老人被卖给人家当女儿，但经常挨打，李老人逃了几次以后最终被爸爸带回家，从此便待在家中，直到1961年出嫁。当时物资匮乏，李老人结婚前为了买一双鞋，排了好久的队。后来李老人在生产队干活，工作特别辛苦，天还没亮就要出去砍柴，如果工作迟到就要扣工分。计划生育政策开始实行以后，如果不去结扎，生产队就不记工分。此外，李老人在这段口述中还唱了不少以前的歌。
  - Liutong Village | 茂名市高州市宝光街道办荷木坡管理区留垌村, 2013
    Liutong Village is located in Gaozhou County, Maoming City, Guangdong Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Wu Haizhu.
    留垌村位于广东省茂名市高州市宝光街道办荷木坡管理区。村民的录像采访人是吴海珠。
    - Jiang Guifang | 江桂芳, 2013
      Jiang Guifang (b. 1920) is a resident of Liutong Village, Guangdong Province. In this interview, Jiang recalls the life during the Great Famine. Though having given birth to five kids, Jiang did not obtain enough nutrients after the labor because of the famine. All she could eat was wild edible herbs rather than meat. As a result, as she grows older, she has developed many diseases. Back then if people in the village got sick, because of poverty, they could not afford a doctor but would just boil some herbs by themselves.
      江桂芳1920年出生，是广东省高州市宝光街道办荷木坡管理区留垌村村民。在这段口述中，江老人回忆了大饥荒时的生活。江老人生了五个儿女，但因为饥荒，每天只能吃野菜，很少吃肉补充营养，导致年纪大了以后有很多病痛。当时如果生病也没有钱请医生，只能自己抓点草药煮水喝。
    - Wu Daiwang | 吴代旺, 2013
      Wu Daiwang (b. 1940) is a resident of Liutong Village, Guangdong Province. In this interview, Wu recalls the life during the Great Famine. Life became difficult since 1958. In addition to the scarcity of food and materials, the workload at the production was also very heavy. People usually had to work till midnight. In order to make extra money, Wu went out to work as a plasterer until he was over 40 years old. Many villagers went to work in other places. They handed in part of their income to the production team and kept the rest. Back then, although some people gave birth to kids, it was in general almost impossible to raise them up. Usually deemed very prestige, doctors, when called in, had to come to the village in sedan chairs.
      吴代旺1940年出生，是广东省高州市宝光街道办荷木坡管理区留垌村村民。在这段口述中，吴老人讲述了大饥荒时期的生活。1958年开始生活变得困难，不仅缺衣少食，生产队的工作也特别辛苦，经常要干活干到三更半夜。为了多赚钱，吴老人出去做水泥工，一直做到四十多岁。村里不少人都出去干活，赚回来的钱一部分给生产队，剩下的自己用。当时虽然有人生小孩，但很难养大。那时候医生很高级，如果要请医生还得抬轿请来。
    - Cheng Wenlan | 程文兰, 2013
      Cheng Wenlan (b. 1936) is a resident of Liutong Village, Guangdong Province. In this interview, Cheng talks about the hardship during the Great Famine. In 1959 when Cheng was planting green vegetables for the production team, although the work was quite heavy, she at least did not need to worry about food. After getting married in 1960, Cheng moved to Hainan Province with her husband. To making a living, they tapped rubber trees for natural rubber. Compared to the hard work, the salaries they earned were very low. As a result, they always starved and their shabby house was only made of tree branches and other materials.
      程文兰1936年出生，是广东省高州市宝光街道办荷木坡管理区留垌村村民。在这段口述中，程老人讲述了大饥荒时的艰苦生活。1959年程老人在生产队种青菜，虽然辛苦但有饭吃。60年结婚以后程老人和丈夫搬到海南，两人当工人，割橡胶树的橡胶，工作辛苦但工资不高，所以经常挨饿，住的房子也只是用树枝等搭出来的。
    - Wu Daisheng | 吴代胜, 2013
    - Wu Daili | 吴代礼, 2013
    - Xu Lanzhen | 徐兰珍, 2013
- Hebei province | 河北省, 2010
  - Dongjieguan Village | 衡水市深州市杨家庄村, 2010
    Dongjieguan Village is located in Shenzhou County, Hengshui City, Hebei Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Jia Nannan.
    东街关村位于河北省衡水市深州市。村民的录像采访人是贾楠楠。
    - Wu Xiuzhe | 吴秀者, 2010
      Wu Xiuzhe (b. 1934) is a resident of Yangjiazhuang Village, Hebei Province. In this interview, Wu recalls the life during the Great Famine. Because of hunger, Wu tried wild herbs, green dates, raw eggplants and cabbage roots.
      吴秀者1934年出生，是河北省衡水杨家庄村村民。在这段口述中，吴老人回忆了大饥荒时期的生活。当时为了填饱肚子，老人吃过野菜、青枣、生茄子、白菜疙瘩。
    - Xue Dajie | 薛大洁, 2010
      Xue Dajie (b. 1937) is a resident of Dongjieguan Village. In this interview Xue recalls the life during the Great Famine. During that time, in order to support the elderly and the children in the family, Xue had to mill the rice and plant grass for the production team.
      薛大洁1937年出生，是河北省衡水东街关村村民。在这段口述中，薛老人回忆了大饥荒时期的生活。当时薛老人家上有老下有小，为了有饭吃，薛老人在家里给生产队碾稻子种草。
    - Rui Zhan | 瑞沾, 2010
      Rui Zhan (b. 1927) is a resident of Dongjieguan Village, Hebei Province. In this interview, Rui talks about the hardship during the Great Famine. With 7 kids to feed, Rui's life was very difficult back then.
      瑞沾1927年出生，是河北省衡水东街关村村民。在这段口述中，瑞老人回忆了大饥荒时期的挨饿经历。当时瑞老人家里有七个孩子，生活十分艰苦。
    - Zheng Lanfang | 郑兰芬, 2010
      Zheng Lanfen (b. 1942) is a resident of Yangjiazhuang Village, Hebei Province. In this interview, Zheng talks about the life during the Great Famine when she was working at the production team. The food given by the production team was far from enough: everyone could only get two jins of wheat when wheat was harvested and then some other grains in the Fall. People had to find wild herbs for extra sustenance and most kids suffered from malnutrition.
      郑兰芬1942年出生，是河北省衡水杨家庄村村民。在这段口述中，郑老人讲述了大饥荒时期的生活。当时郑老人在生产队干活，发的粮食根本吃不饱。收麦子时一人分二斤麦子，到秋天再发点别的粮食，不够吃就只能挖野菜，孩子都因为缺乏营养发育不良。
  - Yangjiazhuang Village | 深州市深州镇杨家庄村, 2010
    Yangjiazhuang Village is located in Shenzhou County, Hengshui City, Hebei Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Jia Nannan.
    杨家庄村位于河北省衡水市深州市。村民的录像采访人是贾楠楠。
    - Jia Futian | 贾福田, 2010
      Jia Futian (b. 1936) was born in Changchun, Jilin Province. During the Siege of Changchun in 1947, Jia fled to Yangjiazhuang Village, Hebei Province with his family. In this interview, Jia talks about the life during the siege and their fleeing, as well as other various experiences from the Liberation to the Cultural Revolution. After the Liberation, Jia went to work in Beijing. In 1958, as a Catholic, Jia expressed his disapproval of the government's religion policies. He was therefore sent to a farm for labor reeducation and experienced the Great Famine on the farm. He was not allowed to return home until 1969. After the Tangshan Earthquake in 1976, Jia went to work in Tangshan as a migrant worker. According to Jia, the work in Tangshan was much more grueling than the farm. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      贾福田1936年出生于吉林省长春市，1947年长春围城时随家人逃难到河北省杨家庄村。在这段口述中，贾老人回忆了长春围城和逃难时的情况，以及解放后直到文革时的各种经历。解放后贾老人在北京工作。1958年，信奉天主教的贾老人因为对宗教政策不满，被发配到农场进行劳动改造，直到1969年才回家，期间经历了大饥荒艰苦的三年。1976年唐山大地震后老人去唐山充民工，据老人回忆，那段经历比在农场劳教时还要辛苦。
    - Jia Fuyong | 贾夫勇, 2010
      Jia Fuyong (b. 1927) is a resident of Yangjiazhuang Village, Hebei Province. In this interview, Jia talks about the life during the Japanese occupation, the Great Famine and the Cultural Revolution. The Japanese arrived in the village in 1937 and stayed for 8 years. Later Jia was forced to join the army when he was still a teenager. During the Great Famine, people ate whatever they could find. In the campaign of "Destroy the Four Olds" during the Cultural Revolution, the birth certificates of Jia's family were accidentally burned, together with books of classical literature.
      贾夫勇1927年出生，是河北省衡水杨家庄村村民。在这段口述中，贾老人讲述了解放前日本人占领时的生活，以及大饥荒和文革时期的经历。日本人1937年到的村里，待了8年。贾老人十几岁就被拉去当兵。大饥荒时，村民找到什么就吃什么。文革时除四旧，烧古书时贾老人家连出生证明都给误烧了。
    - Jia Fukui | 贾夫奎, 2010
      Jia Fukui (b. 1932)is a resident of Yangjiazhuang Village, Shenzhou Town, Shenzhou City, Hebei Province. He is the interviewer's grandfather. In this interview, Jia remembers that his big family lacked manpower to earn work credits during the Great Famine. Back then almost no vegetables could be harvested and all the tree leaves were eaten by the hungry people. Later many people went to work on the dam because they had enough food there. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      贾夫奎1932年出生，是河北省深州市深州镇杨家庄村村民。他是采访者的爷爷。在这段口述中，贾老人回忆了大饥荒时期他的一大家人因为缺少劳动力挣工分而挨饿的经历。大饥荒时期地里都长不出菜，树上的叶子都被人吃光了。后来大家都去挖水库，因为在那里能吃饱饭。
    - Li Yunnu | 李允女, 2010
      Li Yunnu (b. 1926) is a resident of Yangjiazhuang Village, Shenzhou Town, Shenzhou City, Hebei Province. Her body is not well due to the past. In this interview, Li talks about the different kinds of work she did and the starvation she experienced during the Great Famine. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      李允女1926年出生，是河北省深州市深州镇杨家庄村村民。她的身体有很多过去落下的毛病。 在这段口述中，李老人讲述了大饥荒期间她干的各种活和经受的饥饿。
    - Liu Shuming | 刘淑明, 2010
      Liu Shuming (b. 1935) is a resident of Yangjiazhuang Village, Hebei Province. In this interview, Liu talks about the life during two Great Famines around 1944 and 1958-60. She was 9 and went out begging for food with her older sister and they went to several villages without getting enough food. During the People's Commue canteen time, she had to find wild vegetables as there was still severe shortage of food.
      刘淑明1935年出生，是河北省衡水杨家庄村村民。在这段口述中，刘老人讲述了1944年和1958-60年两次大饥荒时期的生活。刘老人9岁时和11岁的姐姐一起去要饭，走几个村子都吃不饱。吃食堂时，挖野菜，同样吃不饱。
- Henan Province | 河南省, 2012-2014
  - Daguo Village | 漯河市临颍县大郭乡大郭村, 2012-2013
    Daguo Village is located in Lingying County, Luohe City, Henan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Guo Rui.
    大郭村位于河南省漯河市临颍县大郭乡。村民的录像采访人是郭睿。
    - Guo Dong | 郭东, 2012
      Guo Dong (b.1919) is a resident of Daguo Village, Linying County, Luohe City, Henan Province. Guo recollects that, in 1942, to escape the labor at home, he went to Xi'an to work at a brick kiln and did not starve. He heard of the breaching of the Yellow River and that many counties were flooded. In 1958, he had parents and children at home, but he could not feed them. Later, he went to work at a machinery factory to support himself.
      郭东（1919年生）是河南省临颍县大郭乡大郭村村民。郭老人回忆了1942年，他说他为了躲拉壮丁，在西安砖窑工作，没在家挨饿。曾听说，黄河决堤，淹了好几个县。1958年，老人家里有父母、孩子，但是自己没能力给家里东西吃。他后来去机械厂做工，养活自己。
    - Guo Diankun | 郭电坤, 2012
      Guo Diankun (b.1934) is a resident of Daguo Village, Linying County, Luohe City, Henan Province. He went to work at Baiguishan Reservoir in 1958 and was back at village in 1960. The production team let someone else to go to the reservoir instead and Guo stayed to raise animals. When people ate at the eating halls, since his mother worked in one of them, he could get some food from her.
      郭电坤（1934年生）是河南省临颍县大郭乡大郭村村民。1958年去过白龟山水库，1960年回村，生产队照顾他，让别人替他去水库，他则在生产队养牲口。吃食堂的时候，他的母亲在食堂里工作，可以拿点东西吃。
    - Gao Xiu'e | 高秀娥, 2012
    - Song Xiutian | 宋秀田, 2012
      Song Xiutian (b.1926) is a resident of Daguo Village, Linying County, Luohe City, Henan Province. In 1942, he ran away from the village to solicit food. His grandfather, elder uncle, and one of the brothers died. In 1948, he took part in the revolution and helped to carry stretchers when Liberation Army fought the Kuomintang's ninth army. In 1949, the chairman of the local agriculture committee was replaced for his problematic lifestyle, and Song announced this decision. The former chairman committed suicide that night, and his family accused Song of illegal inquisition, after which Song was denounced by the party and put into prison for nine months. Later he became a cadre again, taught in the school and supervised many projects.
      宋秀田（1926年生）是河南省临颍县大郭乡大郭村村民。1942年，宋老人逃荒到外地要饭，爷爷、大伯、三哥都死了。1948年，他参加革命，解放军攻打国民党十一师的时候，他去抬担架。 1949年，当地原农会主席因历史和作风问题被组织撤换，他在会上发布这项命令，此人当晚自尽。 死者的家人指控他私设公堂逼供威吓， 老人被"开除出革命队伍"，取消了预备党员资格，也坐了9个月班房。 后来他做了队干部，去学校教书，重新入党，去白龟山水库带工，去铁山、石漫滩等工程。
    - Jin Zhi | 靳枝, 2012
    - Guo Shuming | 郭书铭, 2012
    - Wang Hua | 王花, 2012
      Wang Hua (b.1920) is a resident of Daguo Village, Linying County, Luohe City, Henan Province. Wang was once married to a guard of the Kuomintang and had four children, who all died of sickness when they were little. When the Liberation Army came, Wang's husband was scared to death. After Land Reform, Wang got married with her current husband and had a little girl, who was starved to death around 1958.
      王花（1920年生）是河南省临颍县大郭乡大郭村村民。 王老人曾嫁给国民党军队的警卫员，生了四个孩子，但都长了几岁就生病死去。解放军来的时候，她的丈夫吓死了。土地改革之后，她嫁给了现任丈夫，生了一个小女孩，但是1958年左右饿死了。
    - Wu Ren | 吴任, 2013
      Wu Ren (b. 1941) is a resident of Daguo Village, Linying County, Luohe City, Henan Province. In 1958, Wu did all kinds of labor in the youth team. Her father was sent to Pingdingshan to dig the reservoir. He ran back home because he could not eat enough there. He could not get food from the canteen either, so all the other family members gave him their own portions of food. The 18-years-old Wu went to the reservoir in place of her father, so that her father could work and eat at home. When she was 19, Wu got married during Spring Festival and immediately went back working on the reservoir in winter. In 1960, Wu's sister was starved for too long and died after eating some wheat. Many people died at the reservoir too.
      吴任（1941年生）是河南省临颍县大郭乡大郭村村民。1958年，吴老人在青年队从事各种劳动。她的父亲被派到平顶山挖水库，由于吃不饱，偷跑回家。食堂不给父亲吃饭，一家人省下自己的食物分给他。18岁的吴任提出自己代父亲去挖水库，让父亲留在家里工作，吃食堂。19岁时，吴在春节结婚，然后继续在冬天挖水库。1960年，老人的三妹饥饿过度，吃麦粒后死了。那时候水库也饿死了很多人。
    - Gao Jinghua | 高景花, 2013
      Gao Jinghua (b. 1952) is a resident of Daguo Village, Linying County, Luohe City, Henan Province. During the Famine, Gao was only 7 or 8. The food served at the canteen was like pig food. Her older sisters went to the production team's gardens to steal food. Gao's mother was working at the canteen, and Gao sneakily ate wild vegetables while washing them. She would shut her mouth tightly when cadres came. She remembers that their big pots were taken away but they hid smaller pots and the wheat they stole. Kids at that time were all tiny like dogs because of hunger. Gao got edema once, and a doctor gave her cow feces and soybeans.
      高景花（1952年生）是河南省临颍县大郭乡大郭村村民。高老人饥荒的时候才七八岁，当时食堂的食物和猪饲料一样，不够吃。她的姐姐会去生产队菜园偷东西给她吃。她的母亲在食堂工作，她在洗菜时偷吃野菜，一看到干部就把嘴绷紧。 她还回忆了自己家的大锅被没收，于是他们把小锅和偷的麦子藏起来。那时候的孩子们都被饿得很瘦小，和小狗一样。高老人被饿得身子肿起来，医生给她开的药是牛屎配黄豆。
    - Wang Gai | 王改, 2012
      Wang Gai (b. 1920) is a resident of Daguo Village, Linying County, Luohe City, Henan Province. Wang and her sisters were all sold to be child brides. In 1958, Wang worked day and night, which made her body ache. She carried feces in the morning to gain more work points. During the Famine, Wang tried every kind of tree leaves. Date leaves were too bitter for her. Wang had 4 children with her first husband and 1 child with her second husband. All her children died before maturity. Her youngest daughter was starved at the period of communal canteens.
      王改（1920年生）是河南省临颍县大郭乡大郭村村民。王老人和她的姐妹小时候都做过童养媳。1958年，老人日夜劳动，浑身酸痛。老人清早去拉粪，以换取更多工分。饥荒期间，老人吃了所有种类能吃的树叶，只不再吃太苦的枣树叶。王老人和第一个丈夫生了四个孩子，和第二个丈夫生了一个孩子，但孩子们都没长大就去世了。 老人的小女儿在食堂期间被饿死。
    - Shi Xiangrong | 石香荣, 2013
      Shi Xiangrong (b.1928) is a resident of Daguo Village, Linying County, Luohe City, Henan Province. During the Great Leap Forward, Shi was in her 30s. Her husband was away from home and she was sent to dig the Northern Canal until she got sick. When eating at the canteen, many people would sneakily put sweet potatoes in their own bags, but the interviewer Guo Rui's grandmother didn't dare to take any food. They ate little sweet potatoes and wheat stalks. Shi nearly died because of eating Chinese toon leaves. One son and one daughter of Shi's died within the same year. Once, 9 people died within the same day and there were barely people to dig graves for the dead.
      石香荣（1928年生）是河南省临颍县大郭乡大郭村村民。大跃进期间，石老人三十多岁，丈夫出去工作，于是她被叫去挖北干渠，生病了才回家。村里吃食堂期间，大家都偷偷往袋子里放红薯，就采访人郭睿的奶奶不敢偷东西。他们当时吃红薯疙瘩、麦秸等等，石老人有次吃椿叶差点身亡。她的一个儿子和一个女儿都在那时同一年被饿死。当地有一次一天死九个人，都没有劳动力做坟墓。
    - Chen Lian | 陈莲, 2013
      Chen Lian (b.1933) is a resident of Daguo Village, Linying County, Luohe City, Henan Province. Chen's mother died early. After she grew up, she took care of her father. In both the 1942 and 1958 famine, she went soliciting food. In 1960, her grandparents competed to give their food to her and other children. Later, her grandmother gradually died of hunger. At the commune, Chen worked three shifts a day and worked extra time at the mill after it got dark. Her strained her body so that cadres would not criticize her.
      陈莲（1933年生）是河南省临颍县大郭乡大郭村村民。陈老人母亲去世得早，长大后一直照顾自己父亲。陈老人在1942年和1958年的饥荒时期都出去要饭。1960年，她的外婆和外公争着把东西省下给孩子们，后来外婆慢慢被饿死了。陈老人在公社期间，一天出工三次，天黑了也要去推磨。她累得浑身是伤，不想被干部训斥。
    - Yan Zheni | 闫这妮, 2012
      Yan Zheni (b.1939) is a resident of Daguo Village, Daguo Xiang, Linying County, Luohe City, Henan Province. When people ate at the eating halls, they could only have porridge like noodle soup without noodles. If the porridge was spilled, people would lie on the ground to lick it. People also had various kinds of famine foods. Every family needed to work for credits, so Yan worked in the field at night, leaving her little daughter at home. She could not come back to her except to feed her breastmilk. Dozens of people died every day and villagers did not have time to bury them. Yan's parents also died then. Yan's first husband was from a family of rich peasant, and three people died in their family. She only survived the hunger because she was later married to her second husband, a cadre. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      闫这妮(1939年生)是河南省漯河市临颍县大郭乡大郭村村民。村民集体在食堂吃饭时，每天喝的粥和煮面条的汤水一样，但洒在地上都有人趴着舔。人们只能吃苇根、茨茭芽、豆糁儿等充饥。家家户户都得干活换工分，闫老人当时晚上去田里干活，只能把小女儿留在家中，除非喂奶不能回去。当时一天可以死几十人，来不及被埋葬，老人的父母也是那时候饿死的。她的第一任丈夫家是富农，当时死了三口人，她跟着当干部的第二任丈夫，才没有被饿死。
    - Guo Xueliang | 郭学亮, 2012
      Guo Xueliang (b.1949) is a resident of Daguo Village, Linying County, Luohe City, Henan Province. When people first started to eat in the eating hall，life was easy. They had enough food and got money every month. In the following two years, things got bad and people ate all kinds of famine food to survive. People in their thirties or forties had rely on walking sticks because of hunger. Guo recollects their hard work at the reservoir and their harsh supervisors. His father stole some food and killed himself by jumping into a well, for fear of being denounced, leaving behind his wife and four children. The youngest child was sent away. During the Cultural Revolution, Red Guards were treated well, and went around the country for free to communicate with each other. Guo travelled many places to denounce people.
      郭学亮（1949年生）河南省临颍县大郭乡大郭村村民。1958年刚开始吃食堂的时候生活还好，食物充足，每月还会发钱，后面两年就不行了，人们吃各种东西以度过饥饿，三四十岁的人也得拄着拐杖走路。老人还回忆了当时挖水库的辛苦，和干部严厉的管教。他的父亲偷了点食物，怕被批斗，于是投井自尽，留下家里的老婆和四个孩子，最小的孩子后来被送走了。文化大革命期间，红卫兵的待遇很好，全国串联坐车吃饭都免费，他去了很多地方批斗。
    - Guo Yonghua | 郭永花, 2012
    - Guo Ziyou | 郭自由, 2012
    - Guo Jingye | 郭景业, 2012